so
um
[Music]
hello everyone welcome to the 68th live
episode of ask abhijit it's great to see
you all here
and today i'm going to take questions
from the live chat so get ready with
your questions
before i do that let me just greet you
all let's see who all is there i can see
komal nikhil rajiv ashish
jeet
shubhang singh gurjendra singh dhanya
papu jashin akash rathor
swastika
prithviram rapid gaming atharva
great sir is back
voice of the hidden shiva prasad
gurjender and many more
great to see you all thank you so much
for being here
and let me start with your questions
okay let's see what questions do we have
i can see many questions let's see what
we have
uh
let's take
which question shall we take
okay let's take this question by hassmok
solanki my tamil friend boasts about
kumari condom when i searched online
about it
i found through the wikipedia reference
that it's a myth can you please shed
some light about it on it
kumari condom this is a
myth
or a story a legend that is uh
it's a tamil legend that there used to
be a great mass of land
south
of southern india
which uh supposedly has been swallowed
up by the sea
and that is what they call kumari condom
now
that's
what is
claimed in the legend or the myth now if
you look at the
underwater map of the indian ocean
there is no such land
anywhere near india i mean if you even
if you go thousand kilometers 2000
kilometers away
from the coastline of india in any
direction there is no great submerged
land that is known to have been
submerged anytime in the in the
in the time span of the human species
the human species about is about 1
million 2 million years old homo sapiens
is about 250 000 years old indians
present day indians have been inhabiting
this indian subcontinent for about
60 70 000 years maybe 75 000 years
so that's how we that's how old we are
and there is absolutely no
geological evidence of any submerged
land south of the coastline of india or
east or west of the coastline of india
and therefore one unfortunately has to
conclude
that
as far as the hard scientific evidence
goes this uh
legend
is most likely
99.999 a myth
because there is no evidence for it if
something like this did exist in the
past and it was submerged
under the ocean because of whatever
geological activity or earthquake or any
such thing then you would find evidence
of something like that underwater which
we don't find for instance in dvaraka
there was this legend of dwarka in the
mahabharata and when you go to the
coastline of gujarat
and you go
off the coast of present-day dwarka the
present-day modern city of dwarka you
find an entire underwater city there
which clearly shows that this story is
based in 100 facts the city is there
it's a submerged city it's maybe 8 000
years old or even older who knows
we haven't done any proper
investigations so that
is how you prove
a claim so there is proof and therefore
we accept the fact that the mahabharata
is correct the story is indeed true
there was indeed a city of dwarka which
got submerged under the sea because of
an earthquake or some other cataclysm
in the case of kumari condom i will be
very happy
if any such evidence is found but thus
far there is zero evidence and therefore
as of today we have to conclude that it
is a myth
right
donggar sinchohan says you say gandhi's
feeble movements like dandy march cost
nothing to the british which i agree but
what about the non-cooperation movement
which was intended to cause huge losses
to the british monopoly
what losses were caused
give me a quantitative example of a
single loss that was caused with the
british yes they wanted to uh sell
their textiles in india and there was
this show of burning some textiles and
some products and there may have been
some marginal losses because of that but
where is the major huge loss to the
british monopoly or to the british
economy we have i'm sure we can find uh
records
of the british gdp exports to india etc
yes i'm sure we can find them
and look it up online is there any such
evidence available there is none
there is none otherwise it would all be
written about otherwise the great
historians like mr guha others who extol
mr gandhi's virtues they would have
given the proof and they would be
trumpeting it everywhere that this is
the kind of monetary and financial loss
that the so-called non-cooperation
movement caused to the british there was
no such loss
there was absolutely no such loss right
so that is what i have to say sir uh the
non-cooperation movement was a very nice
thing you know it's very nice to give
very nice titles and names to a project
non-cooperation movement
that's what people do they give very
nice titles
to whatever they are undertaking
especially when they are trying to hide
the real purpose
of the
of the endeavor for instance you have so
many ngos in the world today with
wonderful names
green peace what a brilliant name it is
green and it is peace
but what is the real agenda of
greenpeace if you examine their
activities in the past 30 40 years you
will see they have an entirely different
agenda which well they do uh do they do
uh
take actions that are headline grabbing
attention grabbing and they do
make a big show of being very much pro
uh environment and all that but what is
the outcome of everything they have done
thus far
what is the actual outcome of everything
they have done
that is the question
and once again if you examine the real
details which people can't really do
because it's hard to do that it takes a
lot of effort to do that but when you
examine the real details the real data
you will find that they have had
they have a different agenda most likely
and similarly the non-cooperation
movement was very nice it grabbed lots
of headlines
and it made the entire so-called freedom
struggle look very worthwhile and very
very active
and doing great things but what was the
actual outcome where is this this huge
loss to the british exchequer
where is the huge loss
is there a single data point
that proves this huge loss there is none
right so let's look at the data look at
the numbers
look at the numbers not the narratives
it always boils down to the numbers the
statistics show me the money follow the
money
look at the numbers don't look at
narratives and that should be enough
first principles thinking
first principles thinking think about
principles not about narratives right
so that is what i can say about this
what do you think about the
interpretation of the bhagavad-gita by
the nazis
and the strategies strategies they used
from the gita the expeditions they made
in search of special powers
what is the interpretation they have
made of the bhagavad-gita
i'm not aware of any
um i may be maybe my knowledge isn't
that broad that i don't know about what
interpretations they have made of the
bhagavad-gita but i am not aware of any
what strategies did they use from the
gita well the bhagavad-gita is not a
book of strategies and warfare
it's it's a book
of morality
the righteous way of living
and in such such things right it is not
a book of warfare it is not a book of
strategy
it is a book of personal strategy the
the right values you should follow what
is the right way to follow the path of
dharma and that's what it is about there
are no special hidden mysterious powers
in the bhagavad-gita
the power is that it makes you a better
person a far better person more
righteous person if you follow the path
that is outlined by
shri krishna that's what the
bhagavad-gita is about
right so i am not aware of any such
thing if there is any such thing please
let me know in the comments and i'll be
very happy to educate myself but as far
as i know there is uh from
from within the limits of my knowledge i
am not aware of any special
interpretations any special strategies
or any such thing all right so that's
all i can say
sankalpa gupta says why did hinduism why
could hinduism not spread like buddhism
right so
if you look at the history of indonesia
let's let's take a look at
the map i love the map as you know very
well guys girls
let's go to the map
and the question is why could hinduism
not spread like buddhism so this here is
the map of our world of our planet a
flat representation
this is our land
so where did hinduism not spread so
let's take a look at indonesia if you
can see my mouse pointer this entire
region was hindu
they all practice hinduism today people
are reverting to hinduism many
high-profile cases we have right
like the daughter of the prayer former
president mr sukarno his daughter very
recently reconverted to hinduism the
faith the the culture of her ancestors
so the entirety of indonesia
under the majapahit empire was hindu
nearly 1500 years the philippines you
had hinduism there
and the hinduism they follow in
indonesia is obviously it has elements
of buddhism because i have said this
i forget how many times i've said this
hinduism and buddhism are the same thing
there are more similarities than
differences
the value system is the same the culture
is the same it's all the same it is just
a different way of stating the same
things
so indonesia was entirely hindu
philippines was entirely hindu you have
hinduism that is practiced in thailand
today but it is called about this
country you have the worship of ganesh
of lord shiva in thailand you had the
hinduism in vietnam in cambodia you have
hindu deities that are
worshipped
in japan today with with japanese names
and that is called japanese buddhism
that's what what scholars and historians
call japanese buddhism but you have
hindu deities worshiped in japan today
you have examples of hindu deities which
were worshiped in china as well
and you had hinduism in armenia all
across central asia and hinduism and
buddhism were the same thing
and therefore i would have to point out
that hinduism did spread just like
buddhism but today historians want to
call it only buddhism they are giving it
the tag or the title of buddhism and
that's why we that's why we all believe
because that's what our teachers say our
professors say our textbooks say that it
was only buddhism
the vedas were taught in china the uh
great
scholars who went out of india to china
to spread dharma this they spread not
only buddhism but also vedas they were
all experts in the vedas they taught the
four vedas
and therefore i would have to point out
that hinduism did spread everywhere but
today there is
a certain agenda of
uh
that is uh prevalent in academia
and in politics
and elsewhere
and therefore they are trying to portray
everything as buddhism when you have all
hindu deities all major hindu gods that
are worshipped in japan
for instance saraswati goddess saraswati
devi saraswati is called benzythen
in japan but she is saraswati let me let
me prove it
let me prove it so let us search for ben
zeitung
let us do a google search for ben zaitan
who is benjamin let's take a look okay
let's see let's take a look at wikipedia
what wikipedia has to say wikipedia
typically lies and here here's what it
says bin zaytan is a japanese buddhist
goddess who originated from the hindu
goddess saraswati so they are claiming
she is now
buddhist but she originated from the
hindu goddess saraswati right look at
the images of ben zaitan
there you go that's a japanese version
of saraswati as you can see it's the
same thing right there you go
so that's what i have to say about this
that hinduism spread everywhere it was
dharma that spread all across the known
ancient world
and today they are calling it buddhism
okay
all right
yes swastika asks how was an inferior
culture able to occupy and influence a
superior culture logically it should
have been the opposite then how was the
abrahamic cult able to spread and
destroy dharmic culture almost all over
the world okay so once again first
principles thinking
first principles thinking what do you
mean by inferior what do you mean by
superior what is the definition in your
head
of inferior and superior
because you are very
learned
does that alone make you superior
if you have great universities
great viharas mahaviharas
great scholars immense libraries is that
enough to make you superior
if you have a great prosperous
fabulously wealthy nation is it enough
to make you superior
or do you also need political unity
and a massive military to safeguard your
immense wealth don't you need that
and if you don't need that can you truly
call yourself superior
and what makes somebody inferior is a
lack of culture and manners enough to
make you inferior but what if these
barbarians who are who have no culture
what if they have
a massive
well-oiled well-organized military
machine
it means they are outstanding
in the military domain
and then if you have a wonderful culture
wonderful civilization extremely wealthy
brilliant scholars great libraries great
great universities but they are
disunited
and they have neglected the military
dimension of the world
then they are going to be wiped out by
the barbarians you see this happen over
and over and over and over again in
human history
it happened to rome it happened to
greece
it happened to so many others and it
happened to india in the past 1000 years
because despite being culturally and
civilizationally superior we lacked we
lost the political unity and we
neglected the military sphere and more
importantly we forgot the teachings of
vishnu gupta chanakya destroy your enemy
at all costs
that's how it happens and once the
barbarians infiltrate your lands they
will influence you they will destroy
your culture and try to superimpose
their culture on yours
that is the story
in brief
so it is not enough to have a great
civilization to have a great culture
what is the point of having beautiful
universities great culture great arts
dance music wonderful libraries millions
of books what is the point of having
incredible wealth if you are not willing
to defend it
this my friends is the lesson of history
there is no point getting wealthy there
is no point creating great culture if
you do not pay equal attention to
defense to civilizational defense and
civilizational offense
and that's what we forgot that's what we
lacked and that's why barbarians were
able to overrun us and destroy our
culture and try to
try to superimpose their culture on ours
all right
riddhiman sen says where the pyramids of
giza made by advanced human civilization
or some alien kinds of stuff
uh i would be so happy if there was some
alien involvement since i was a little
kid seven six seven years old i was
fascinated with aliens
and isn't it amazing if there was some
kind of alien contact that would be the
most amazing cultural or species level
or planetary interplanetary interstellar
contact that we could ever imagine but
unfortunately we have been able to find
no
not a single piece of evidence of any
alien presence on earth there is some
thing that looks like tangential
uh circumstantial evidence some egyptian
hieroglyphics that seem to depict some
weird thing like
something that looks like something out
of star wars some space vehicle or
something and in some other places also
you get carvings etc of something that
looks like flying saucers but is it
enough to claim there was aliens here
there was alien visitation it's not
enough it is something that looks like
that that's what's called superficial
circumstantial or tangential evidence
what is real evidence you find an actual
alien artifact or you meet an alien
person
an alien being that is called genuine
hard evidence verifiable evidence in
controvertible evidence and that is what
we lack and therefore
what i can say is that there is no
evidence
of
any alien involvement on our planet in
the construction construction of the
pyramids of giza now these pyramids are
fantastic very interesting monuments let
me let me share that
okay let me share my screen
these are the pyramids of giza take a
look from above let me see pyramids from
above
very interesting these this is here a
depiction of
a
satellite image of the pyramids
so these are monumental
uh this is monumental architecture if
you see it close by you can even see
that there is a certain amount
of relief there so it's not entirely
flat there is a slight curvature so this
is this was created very precisely
there was a great deal of precision a
great deal of uh
of architectural knowledge of geometric
knowledge and they were able
to lift these immense blocks of stone
and place them all the way up top and we
are unable to figure out
how these ancient egyptians
uh
created were able to engineer this
marble because to to lift such enormous
multiple ton blocks of
stone
all the way up there you would need
modern equipment and therefore we are
not able to figure out essentially how
they managed to do this
there is no
way to
figure out how they have done this so
that is one of the big mysteries what we
can tell about the pyramids is that this
represents an imperial
culture
these pyramids served no civic purpose
social purpose nothing that served
society it was merely to glorify the
dead kings of egypt the dead pharaohs of
egypt so you can tell very clearly that
this is an example of an imperial
culture
in which the kings of egypt were
regarded as gods and their rule was
supreme
and uh most likely these pyramids it is
well it is the western historians who
say this they were most likely
made created built by slave labor they
have found uh bodies of dead slaves even
children
over here so that tells you what kind of
society it was it was a it was
one could imagine a reasonably brutal
society uh
what you would call today a dictatorial
society very different from ancient
india in ancient india you find that all
the ancient monuments had us had a civic
purpose a social purpose a public
purpose the greatest monuments in the
saraswati civilization all the biggest
building etc they were public buildings
that served the public
and in contrast to that in ancient egypt
the biggest monuments were they were
meant to glorify the the god kings
so that's what i can say about this but
there is no evidence of any uh
alien involvement in the construction of
these structures so all i can say that
although we do not know how they were
able to create these enormous structures
there is no evidence of alien
involvement in that so most likely it
was
a reasonably advanced
civilization that did this the egyptians
okay let's uh
yeah i have answered some so many
questions i have answered
uh
so let me explain how to search
for
questions i have already answered just
briefly i'll
show that
so one second so if you
let me share this so this is my channel
okay let me remove the question
okay so this is my channel here if you
want to search for
if you have a question for me
and you're not sure if i've answered it
or not please go to the search button
here
and for example if you want to uh ask a
question about indus valley type indus
and see what comes up so as you can see
there are i've answered a bunch of
questions about indus
indus indus valley etc if you have a
question about aryans or in invasion etc
search for that you can even do it on
your cell phone so please
try and search
for uh questions i i have answered
hundreds of questions thus far i have
more than 700 short clips on my channel
already it's going to keep coming so
please do that i have answered lots of
questions it's quite likely
that i have already answered a question
that you may already have
right
other says it is is it possible to crack
the iit-jee advanced exam in six months
from basics to advance i think i
answered this very specific question
of one or two weeks ago it is certainly
possible sir it is possible
i don't know where you stand in terms of
your knowledge in terms of your
understanding of mathematics and physics
etc but as long as you have a good basic
understanding of mathematics physics at
that level at that level then you should
be able to crack it very easily in six
months if you study hard and digital
diligently and if you study smart very
much possible so all the best sir good
luck and go forth
they just says what is the origin of the
word brahmanism is it a racist
propaganda it is a neologism
it is a word that has been created by
western historians and other people with
a certain agenda of trying to to break
up hinduism in lots of small components
because their ultimate agenda is to
destroy indian culture indian
civilization so they want to create
schisms in indian society they want to
create divisions artificial divisions
within indian society they want to make
the so-called see first of all they have
created this four level caste system
india had a very very detailed
multi-faceted multi-leveled varnajati
system varna was your occupation jathi
means your lineage it was a very
detailed complicated system nobody
actually cared what varnajathi you were
from the you only recorded what
what lineages you were from and that's
what that's what it was now the british
created they could not understand it
they could not comprehend it so they
divided indian society into four
categories based on something that was
written in the past in one of the
ancient indian books
and that's how this thing was created
and then they made it mandatory to
identify
one of these four so-called castes and
today it is enforced all across india by
the government and that's why we believe
also because of our textbooks that we
were always a caste-east country so they
have created these artificial divides
and today's colonial
system continues that perpetuates that
and the academics have a very sinister
agenda all these university professors
humanities people humanities individuals
they have this
uh agenda to break up indian society
because they are paid for it by external
forces and also internal forces so there
are so many enemies of indian culture
and civilization
so that's why they create this these
these
new new concepts brahmanism
they say that the brahmins were the most
evil
uh people in indian society they
controlled all the wealth all the power
all the knowledge and they
manipulated indian society in a way that
uh various people were oppressed and
marginalized and they are now calling
hinduism's brahmanism so that they can
term brahminism as evil without having
to call hinduism evil
see if you call hinduism evil you it is
not acceptable most in most parts of the
world to call any religion evil and
therefore they have created this new
idea of brahminism and they want to call
that evil just like they have created
this new term of hindu which is now evil
but hinduism is fine hinduism is fine as
long as you're passive you never speak
up for yourself and you never raise your
head so hinduism is okay okay tolerable
but hindu is bad similarly brahmanism is
evil but hinduism
it is just different ways of attacking
your culture your religion your
civilization so it is yeah it is
certainly propaganda the origin is 100
colonial and every single academic
professor etc who speaks about dramatism
who writes about brahmanism is an enemy
of indian civilization mark my words
okay
all right um
ayu says what's my take on mr gandhi
referring to the great sardar singh
assassinating the monster general dyer
as an act of insanity i mean what can i
say about what mr gandhi said mr gandhi
i think i have made it very clear what
mr gandhi's agenda was
and yeah therefore the assassination of
the great monster was according to him
an act of insanity i mean i am not sure
if he actually said that this is what
you're saying most likely it must be
true i haven't
i haven't studied everything in the
world i have never been really
interested in the so-called independent
struggle because we never got
independence and i have never been
interested in individuals like mr gandhi
mr nehru and so on and so forth but i do
have reasonable amount of knowledge
more than most people i i imagine
so i haven't come across this particular
quote of mr gandhi but since you're
saying it i'm assuming it's
clearly
something he said
and therefore it again
brings out another facet of mr gandhi uh
i'm not sure if he condemned what mr
dyer did general dyer uh even if he may
have
some
uh condemnation of the jalan walabag
massacre i'm sure it was not strong
enough and he did not take any actual
real-world actions as opposed to issuing
statements
and
then this this
characterizing the assassination of dire
as an act of insanity i mean i just
don't understand it the guy
dire killed so many indians innocent men
women children
and if he is assassinated what's the bad
thing about it why is it bad
he was never being he was never going to
be brought to justice by the british
or by indians because at that time india
was still
officially
an enslaved nation
and therefore the only recourse indians
had
for justice was to assassinate the
monster
and why is it an act of insanity i mean
i simply cannot understand
why it is an act of insanity
rudra says how to manage the mental
health and how do you manage your mental
health my mental health has been worse
since the
from the last two years because of
loneliness i'm very sorry to hear this
i have never had any mental health
health issues i mean this is something
that i've only heard from social media
and the media and all that that people
have mental health issues i have never
struggled
with depression or any such issues so i
am not the right person to ask this i am
by nature a very very positive person i
keep myself very busy i have many
projects to work on
since i am so busy i have i don't have
the time to think about oh i am
am i feeling bad bad all that i have
always been an extremely positive person
even when things are not fine
so
maybe it's a matter of attitude but i am
not the right person to give advice
about mental health issues or any such
problems because i am not a qualified
professional in this matter so please my
friend rudra i am very sorry that you're
not feeling well i wish you the very
best of luck at the very best of health
please consult a qualified professional
and get the requisite help
and i'm sure you will be fine i mean i
can see your your picture you look quite
young uh loneliness you're saying well
i'm not quite sure what caused the
loneliness
uh the
the the solution to loneliness is to
make friends and mingle with people
and interact socially so if you can
manage to do that that may certainly
alleviate the issue but my
simple suggestion and my request is
please seek help go to a qualified
good mental health professional and
since you are so young i am sure your
problem will be resolved very quickly
please please do that
and all the best my friend all the best
i wish you nothing but the very best
of luck and health
all right let's take some more questions
um
[Laughter]
what kind of oil do you use for my hair
i have no oil in my hair right now i
rarely use oil i think um
i think coconut oil is supposed to be
the one of the best
for for health that's what we know for
thousands of years
i think indians have always used coconut
oil for health and there is amla oil and
other things as well if you want to know
the best oil for your hair
seek advice from an ayurvedic
practitioner or from ayurvedic knowledge
that is now available freely online so i
personally don't use hair oil very much
so
anyhow that's the answer
okay let's take some more questions um
okay sports
uh says my insight on which sports were
played in ancient india was india's
superpower and sports back then so in
the old days there was no world cup or
anything because the world was a smaller
place smaller because we did not have
the kind of transportation and
communication we have today right we did
not have aircraft we did not have a
trains
and we did not did not have the kind of
communication uh technologies that we
have today i am speaking right now in
this room
in my study
live to all of you and i'm i'm able to
instantaneously reach out to people all
across the world right
so in the ancient days we did not have
that people who lived in india
may not know anyone who lived in greece
people who lived in greece may not know
anybody who lived
therefore there was no
the the kind of interconnectedness we
have today
wasn't there in the past and therefore i
imagine there were no world cups of any
sports and all that but what sports were
played in in india
so i think the support of kabaddi is a
very ancient sport it is played in india
and in iran as well which is very
interesting because the iranians are our
brothers and sisters aren't they i mean
we are the same ethnicity the same
ethnic group the indo-iranians they call
it but uh
in old days they would have called the
indians and iranians as the aryans the
arya people all of india north south
east west all of us and our persian
brothers brothers and sisters now so so
kabaddi is a very ancient sport uh what
other sports were there polo is a very
ancient sport that comes out of india it
it originates in manipur
the world's oldest polo ground is in the
city of imphal in manipur so polo comes
from india
and i am sure there were lots of
different martial arts in india
we know that the origin of kung fu is in
india it's now called kung fu it was
brought to china by the great uh monk
by the great dhyan master
in rishi
buddhi dharma
so he went to china with the intention
of translating sanskrit sutras and
knowledge into chinese but then he found
certain conditions in the monastery
there and therefore he was forced to
teach all the monks in ancient indian
martial art which has now disappeared
from india and that was further
developed in china in the shaolin temple
and it is now known as kung fu so we had
martial arts if you look at various uh
if you look at various dances in india
you can see glimpses of ancient martial
arts in there
you know what here is the secret
all dance
originates
in
fighting
all dance originates in martial arts
if you look at uh in western india in
gujarat they have this dandiya right
dandiya and ras and garba and all that
if you look at the moves those are sword
fighting moves
so it is most likely something that
originated with ancient rajput warriors
some maybe a thousand plus more years
ago in gujarat possibly
and the same dance is found all the way
north in afghanistan the same music the
same moves
so there were clearly great martial arts
traditions in india which were wiped out
by the foreign invaders of india in the
last 1000 years of humiliation
but clearly there were many sports many
martial arts prevalent all across india
we have kalai payutu in in kerala today
it is still present thank god there are
martial arts still present in manipur
which were suppressed by the british but
some of it still survives and if you
look at the story of lord krishna
playing on the banks of the yamuna river
the ball falls into the water he goes to
retrieve it and there's this great snake
there great the great snake kali
so that story what sport is lord krishna
playing
he is hitting a ball with a bat
isn't he
and this is several thousand years ago
so once again there was a sport that
looked very much like the what we call
cricket today
ball and bat that was played during the
time of the mahabharata during the
childhood of lord krishna and it is
clearly a sport that was very old even
then
and people say that cricket is is an
indian sport that the british invented
well i disagree it's always been an
indian spot hitting a ball with a bat
so that's what i can say in brief about
what sports were played in ancient india
we have lost so much of the ancient
knowledge ancient information into data
but we can still see glimpses of various
things there is cupboard there is cocoa
there is polo
cricket backball
there is a spot like hockey that is
played in manipur in a different style
so there is so much if if our historians
and anthropologists etc would only look
around
take their heads out of their books
which are written by western authors and
actually look around and do some real
research we would find a gold mine a
wealth of knowledge about our past so i
hope that you youngsters
you in a few years you will be the
leaders in these fields and you will
bring out all this lost information that
is still there but it's hidden below the
surface and it's hidden among the noise
and the propaganda
okay
hi radhiman i think you're asking this
question lots of time
okay so the question is
please tell us about the majapahit
empire of indonesia and why did the last
king decide to convert to islam despite
their barbaric rule elsewhere i i'm not
sure i mean this is a part of history i
have personally not studied in depth and
therefore i will not be able to give you
the answer of why he converted most
likely there was a great deal of trade
between the arabs and the
people of indonesia the majapahit empire
so something like that i will return to
you
after studying this in in more detail
and i will give you a clear answer so
let us let's leave this last part of the
question for the future
but what was the majapahit empire of
indonesia it was the great the greatest
empire in the history of indonesia it
was a hindu empire they regard it as the
pinnacle
of their entire existence of their
entire history the greatest golden age
of indonesia was the time of the
majapahit empire it was a very strong
empire military strong culturally strong
they were mainly shaivites
they worshipped the great lord shiva the
great mahadeva and they also had
elements of what we call buddhism
so that's what it was they had they
built so many wonderful temples
all across indonesia
and even today you find elements of that
so that was the majapahit empire i think
it's pinnacle was in the 13th 12th 13th
14th centuries if i am not mistaken
somewhere around that era i think i will
revisit this question with more data
and i will answer that but that's in
brief about the majapahit empire
and i will revisit this for sure all
right so good question
shikhar sarov says can you share your
vipassana experience
where did you do it i never went on a
vipassina retreat i was taught the
technique by
a buddhist monk from myanmar more than
20 years ago so i was taught the
technique i have done this on and off
not as often and as rigorously as i
would like to do it i have never gone on
a 10-day silent retreat and therefore
i cannot consider myself or call myself
somebody who is an expert in this i know
the principles i know the technique i
know how it's done but i am not
somebody who has risen to higher levels
you know in games you have achievement
unlocked and next level and all that
well i am still at a reasonably basic
level i'm not a beginner by any means
but
um i am
disappointed that i have not gone uh and
done this more
than i
have thus far
so uh
it is something i have done privately at
home only it is very difficult to do it
when there is so much
so much activity around you then there
are people around you when there's noise
and all that the best time to do it is
is deep in the middle of the night when
there's no noise there is no disturbance
etc
but once you reach higher levels all the
disturbances
all the distractions disappear and melt
away but i have unfortunately not
attained that level yet
so
there is so much that i can improve
about myself so that's in brief about my
vibration experience it is one of the
most ancient or meditation techniques
in the known universe
uh people call it a buddhist technique
well that's not the case it is an indian
dharmic technique it
it predates the time of gotham buddha by
thousands of years
it is the technique that lord buddha
himself used in order to attain
enlightenment nirvana he used multiple
techniques but some techniques did not
work for him eventually he settled on
the technique of vipassina
which is clearly just one form of dhyana
and that's what he used to progress
upwards and reach the
pinnacle of existence which is
enlightenment
nirvana so
so that's what it is and that's my
little experience with that i am by no
means an accomplished master in that
here we go
so tejas asks can we really call the
crash of the
mi-17 helicopter that carried
cds general bipin singh ravath an
accident
um yeah
so there are three possibilities how
many let's say three
one possibility
is that
this crash
happened because there was a technical
slag technical fault in the helicopter
that is one possibility
the second possibility is that there was
some freak weather incident
some
some strange weather condition
one in a thousand one in a million
weather condition that caused the
helicopter to crash
the third possibility
is there is sabotage
so let's take possibility one that there
was some technical malfunction in the
helicopter well this is a new helicopter
it's not an ancient clunky old russian
helicopter it's it was a helicopter that
was i heard it was purchased in 2009
which means it's reasonably new
it's one of the most advanced
uh military helicopters that russia has
it is built like a tank it has seen
service
in for thousands of hours in all kinds
of different climates and terrains
it can take
machine gun fire it can take sniper fire
it can even take rocket launcher fire
and survive that it's built like a
bloody tank that's what it is it can i i
hear it can climb to very high altitudes
i believe it can even climb all the way
to station glacier so this helicopter is
a brilliant helicopter it doesn't crash
like that
so
the technical snag thing if it is true
well then the question arises who is
maintaining the helicopter
right
is the is there
so so that is one problem there is one
possibility there was a technical snag
and technical snags happen when you
don't maintain a helicopter properly so
let's keep that aside
uh possibility too is that there was a
freak weather incident which well nobody
or there were many eye witnesses they
saw
no freak weather no strange weather and
therefore we can rule the bad weather
out this helicopter can survive any kind
of weather conditions
so that is number two and number three
is sabotage
now if this thing was sabotaged
then how was it sabotaged
right that's the question
how do you sabotage a helicopter well
you need access to the helicopter you
need to be somebody who has
regular access to the helicopter and
then you need to be able to open up the
helicopter and go inside and make
something you know make some changes in
the machinery either loosen some bolts
or screws or something or or cut some
wires or snag or something like that or
maybe plant some explosive device small
one which will detonate at some time it
means that you had somebody in this
hypothetical scenario of sabotage it
means there was somebody who
had
access officially to the helicopter
even in the case of a technical snag it
means somebody messed up somebody who's
in charge of maintenance messed up and
then there is the very unlikely theory
in some circles i hear this
that somebody on board the helicopter
did something
so these are four possibilities now i am
not saying any of these possibilities
are correct but if you want to examine
an accident you have to look at it
methodology methodically logically and
with a completely cold mind
no emotions
every possibility has to be considered
contemplated and ruled out
so i am sure this is what's happening
right now i don't have the answers my
friends
i am showing what are the four
possibilities
one is technical malfunction technical
snag which means somebody messed up
number two bad weather extremely
unlikely we can rule it out number three
sabotage who had access to the
helicopter number four very very
unlikely
that somebody on board did something
these are the four possibilities
now we will know when the proper inquiry
is done we have the black black boxes
it's not a very extensive crash site
it's a small crash site the helicopter
did not disintegrate over several miles
so we have all the uh
remains of the helicopter i think we
have one survivor i hope that the
gentleman is still alive i hope so so we
can enter the the army will interview
the person and find more details
now did general ravath have enemies
hell yeah he had enemies
and some people are speculating that
because he was making these big
statements against china and pakistan
that's why here enemies you know what
if you have
let's consider this hypothetical case
you have a general
hypothetical case
you have a general who is completely
incompetent but he makes very big
statements every day
will your enemies
be bothered by that
do your enemies care about big
statements words are words no one cares
about words it is actions that matter
if you have a person who is completely
incompetent but is very big on words
every day he makes very strange very
strong statements your enemies won't
care they'll be very happy to have a
person like that
on the other hand if you have a person
who doesn't make big statements but he
is actively working to make the indian
armed forces very strong that guy is a
cause of concern for your enemies
and general dipin singh rawat was a man
of
action he was clearly
taking actions decisive actions that
were very harmful for our enemies
words don't matter my dear friends
actions only matter words
ignore words
ignore words look at actions
so general ravath he had a big challenge
big task we have three services the army
the navy the air force these are totally
different environments in the past there
was no coordination between them there
was no communication between them at uh
at the level that you would want there
to be
very different systems very different
bureaucracies very different mindsets
but in a country like india you need all
three to be closely integrated and work
as one big machine
and that was never there until today and
when general robert was appointed as the
cds in 2019 it was his task
to take these three
very disparate
institutions
organizations and bring them together
and unify them into a coherent hole
into an integrated well-oiled
military machine
and that was a work in progress and i am
certain he was doing a brilliant job at
that and that is why he posed an
enormous threat
to our enemies who are our enemies
china and pakistan
right
and i think by no by now everybody knows
what happened in early 2020 the cds of
taiwan died in a helicopter crash in in
early 2020
and now general ravath
dies in a helicopter crash in a very
good helicopter a helicopter that is new
and a very good machine
and therefore
like i said some days ago on twitter i
don't believe in accidents i don't
believe in coincidences
so let the government do its job let the
inquiry committee etc do their job
the
truths may most likely never be revealed
to the public which it which it should
not this is a very sensitive matter
right this is a very sensitive matter we
cannot disclose the truth
the government cannot disclose the truth
to the public because then our enemies
will also know what the government knows
and therefore there will be some
generic statements
as there should be and whatever
consequences
are there will be done in secret but i
hope there are consequences i
see i don't have any answers
i don't have any real information or
data as to what this was
but the possibility of sabotage and a
foreign hand or maybe even an internal
hand exists
it cannot be rule out we have lots of
enemies within the country as well
as you have seen lots of people in india
have openly celebrated the death of
general b pins
even lots of retired army personnel
have celebrated the death of general
weapons gravath so there is no shortage
of enemies outside the country and
within the country
and these are the issues
the government needs to tackle i'm sure
they are taking actions to tackle this
these actions will never be revealed to
the public as they should not these
things have to be kept
classified but i hope that
the truth will be uncovered at that
level
and the
required actions will be taken it is a
terrible loss to the country but and i
hope
that the government will move quickly to
appoint a new cds because see when you
have a great leader of an organization
there always has to be a succession plan
always
what if something happens to this leader
there has to be a number two who is
ready to take over at a moment's notice
when you look at prime minister modi he
has at least two people who are ready
who are waiting in the wings in case in
the
unforeseen circumstances situation
that mr modi may have to possibly step
aside
for whatever reason someday
we have a couple of people who can take
over immediately
similarly i hope
that there were a couple of people under
general bipin rawat who are in a
position right now to take over
immediately and continue the great work
he was doing the the hallmark of a great
leader is that he or she produces more
great leaders
uplifts the right people and creates
a line of people who can take over and
replace them without any hassles
so that is the hallmark of a great
leader
i am
we know that general bipin since was a
great soldier a great leader he was the
right man for the job and i hope that he
had groomed
one or two people at least who could
have replaced him at a moment's notice
and i hope the appointment of the new
cds will be done soon because this is a
matter of national matter of national
interest national security
i know it's a terrible tragedy
we i have paid tribute to general ravath
i pay tribute to him again great man
and now it is time for the government to
quickly move forward
and appoint a new cds who will carry on
the great legacy of general ravath
so that is what i can say about this
all right
let's take some more questions
bobi says it was no accident it's got to
be the bears
well i don't know about the bears it
could be the dragons it could be the i
don't know somebody else i
i have my suspicions but i will not
speculate here but yeah it is
possible that it was not an accident
possible that there was some
some other
reason for the crash
all right let's take some more questions
i heard that indians only have an indian
specific clade of r1a z93 and central
agents and europeans have for the
diversity of the wider r1 family rna
family how true is this you haven't
answered
abhijit you haven't answered
okay
uh so r1 z93 okay let me tell you um
the facts
there are certain uh
uh
research projects going on right now
all right that whose results haven't
been published
you must have heard of dr nirajirai
dr niraj rai is one of the world's
leading
molecular biologists
geneticists archaeogeneticists
and there is a project going on right
now
uh about to to understand the genetic
makeup of the indian population at large
and the results of this study haven't
been published yet and what is what is
going to show
i know because i've spoken to him
what it is going to show is that india
has the highest diversity of r1a
anywhere in the
world anywhere on the planet indians
have the highest
uh percentage of r1a among the indian
population and the highest diversity
inside r1a so you have z9393 and you
have all kinds of other
clades subclades etc within this genetic
lineage
so the data that you are referring to
i'm not sure where you found it
but it is not consistent with the facts
and even the published facts that we
have today
show that india has higher diversity of
rna than europeans and central asians
so that is the answer to it
and there are more pieces of evidence
that are coming out soon in the next
minute maximum two three years which is
which are going to put this entire
narrative of r1a being a foreign thing
completely to bed completely to rest r1a
is 100
an indian genetic lineage it is an
indian origin genetic lineage and the
ancestor of r1a
if you go back up up the up the genetic
tree is haplogroup f
and
90 more than 90 percent of
non-african males are descendants of
haplogroup f
group f
is an indian origin haplogroup more than
90 percent of non-african men
are descended
from the indian origin genetic lineage
haplogroup f so i think it sets
everything to rest
and so so let's wait another couple of
years two three years
and we will have a bunch of genetic
research papers that will come out which
will completely put to rest this entire
false narrative of r1a being out from
outside india and the aryan invasion or
migration or tourism or picnic
into india it's going to be completely
put to rest so i hope that answers your
question to a certain extent let's wait
for the papers to be published
all right
pawan says do you think that hindi
literature and other regional literature
literature is dead because whenever i
see any book release these days all are
in english unfortunately
you are right
indian regional literature is
almost dead you don't see any any
you know
high quality literature coming out
in malayalam
in gujarati
in hindi
in odia in punjabi in assamese
in magadhi
in kannada
you don't see any of this happening
there are
everybody who has a literary mindset
wants to write in english because that's
where the eyeballs are that's where the
attention is that's what the money is if
you are a great writer but you don't
earn money then you
well then there's no point writing so
money financial considerations are at
the heart of everything you do in life
and the money is in english literature
only
so yeah you are absolutely right this
entire focus on english is destroying
india's
rich
incredibly rich linguistic diversity it
is wiping it out
very unfortunate that's why i keep
advocating
that india's education system has to be
a two language education system the
civilizational language sanskrit and the
mother tongue education has to be only
in these two things english should be
optional after a certain age if you want
to take english or french or german or
swahili
or whatever else take it up after a
certain age is an optional thing but
your primary
basic education has to be in the mother
tongue and in sanskrit and that's it
that's how it has to be
so yeah that's what i can say
ordinary anime fan says why is the indus
violet script and the easter island
script why do these two scripts look so
similar even though both places are far
away from each other you are right there
is a significant striking similarity
between the indus valley saraswati
valley script and the so-called rongo
rongo script of the easter island people
that script is is uh extinct now and the
people who live on the island are no
longer able to read it because they were
they're they're
traditions were wiped out by by invaders
european union invaders
so
why is there the similarity well i don't
have an answer nobody has an answer but
there is certainly a similarity they do
look strikingly similar at least in some
glyphs and all that
so
i think the the
solution to
the when will we have an answer the
solution is we need to decipher both the
scripts
as of today nobody has successfully
deciphered the saraswati sindhu script
or the wrong script
so if
both these scripts are deciphered then
we will know whether there is any actual
similarity or was it just some kind of
coincidence of course coincidences don't
really exist but that's what i can say
as of today we don't have the answer
no linguist no historian has the answer
as to why there is this similarity and
that's a fascinating question
that's why
these are the questions that should
drive research these are the questions
that fascinate everybody
so why aren't historians focusing on
these questions
they have no connection with the real
world these academics they they live in
their small private universes
in the private world and they only
strive
to impress each other
but they serve they no longer serve any
useful purpose to society they are not
solving
the big problems they're not answering
the questions that people have very very
valid and legitimate questions that's
why academia is dying a slow death and
it deserves to
all right let's take some other
questions
why did europeans not colonize the
chinese region well they tried to
they tried to
but
you see
take a look at the colonization of india
it took a number of centuries
india was already broken by the turkic
invaders and occupiers who invaded india
over a long period of time and then
occupied much of it and destroyed india
broke india right india still survived
but it was a broken civilization
india was already softened up
over several centuries by the turks and
that's when the europeans came in
and they were able to play their games
divide and conquer
the marathas were rebuilding at the time
they had already reconquered much most
of india from the turks
but it was a work in progress and they
also suffered from these problems of
disunity
and politics and all that regrettably it
could have been so great so the
europeans the british were able to take
advantage of that and they were they
were able to slowly colonize india they
started with bengal
then
south of india they had a station in
western india in surat in gujarat and
slowly slowly it took several centuries
for for the entire colonization to
happen
they did not have sufficient time in
china if uh
so so you have heard i've spoken about
the opium wars on this channel search it
search on my channel about the opium
wars china's so-called century of
humiliation so there was certainly
certainly uh
this involvement by the colonial powers
the the
british the americans were also involved
in humiliating china
you know and so on so forth so they
tried they did not have sufficient time
if they had another 100 years they may
have succeeded but they did try
kardashev scale i have answered this two
three times at least so please look at
my previous answers
uh it is about
this question i have answered these
questions okay i have answered these
questions at least two three times i
think i have more than two or three
short clips on this channel so please
search there and you will find the
answer
kanai butt says what did the normal
ordinary houses look like say in 2500 bc
in ancient india what does their
engineering compare
with greece and egypt
so if you look at the architecture that
survives in the saraswati hindu region
sapta sandu region
especially in the large cities like
harappa mohenjo-daro kalimangan and uh
etc you find evidence of multi-storied
buildings multi-storied houses
so that's around 2500 bc or and even
before that before that i'm sure there
were single storied houses but at the
height of the
saraswati sindhu civilization saraswati
era
of india civilization you had
multi-story buildings
in
the great cities i'm sure even in the
smaller
settlements but the multi-story
buildings were like the mumbai's and
tokyos and new york's of those times
those big cities
etc those were the great great cities of
the time the new yorks the san
franciscos the tokyos
the mumbai's the bellies of the time so
you had these multi-storied buildings
and even in the smaller settlements
smaller towns villages you had very
well organized cities and so on
so that's what i can say you people did
live in very modern
cities
very modern houses multi-storied houses
you had brilliant drainage systems
far those drainage systems of 2500 bc
were superior to the drainage systems
you have in modern indian cities the
town planning city planning was superior
to the town planning that you have in
modern indian cities today 2021
they even had flush toilets
in
those cities
over 4000 years ago so the flush toilet
was invented in india and so on
so the there was a
great level a great deal of uh
technological sophistication
very high level of research and
development a standardization of weights
and measures and all that which
indicates it was a very very
technologically scientifically advanced
phase of india's civilization
okay
some more questions
uh super saiyan says do you think hitler
flew to argentina because when the
soviet test remains of hitler when the
soviets tested the remains of hitler
they found it was not hitler dna was
duplicate of hitler
well
dna testing
was invented in the 1980s 1990s it
became
something that became part of law
enforcement and
identification of people of
identification of human remains in the
1990s late 90s and from the 21st century
onwards
so when the soviets in
in the second world war in the 1940s
1950s 1960s 1970s there was no dna
fingerprinting there was no dna testing
dna itself was discovered in the 1950s
or 60s i think 60s it was
watson and crick
i'm not sure which decade 50s or 60s i
think
let me just quickly check it
watson and click when did they discover
dna
um the discovery of dna 1950s it was
1950s so the uh historical event that
you were referring to referring to
happened in the 1940s before dna was
even discovered
so there was no way for the soviets to
to know for sure this whether this burnt
human body belonged to adolf hitler or
somebody else
and they have i don't think they have
made their discoveries public
or if they have we're not sure if they
have revealed the entire truth so i'm
not sure there is still confusion and
controversy about whether they what
happened to hitler's body it is believed
the soviets found the body and they took
it somewhere and disposed of it in some
manner gave it a burial or something i
don't know for sure but there was
certainly
no dna testing available
to
identify a body maybe they could have
identified from
dental history or whatever if they had
access to that
so there is still some question
there there are still some questions
about whether adolf hitler died
in a suicide in 1945 i think 45 yeah
or whether he managed whether it was a
hoax it was an elaborate hoax that he
created in order to escape to argentina
there are some claims by some people
that he did indeed escape to argentina
and live out his life there well those
claims have not been corroborated and
proven
so
at the end of the day we don't know
for sure what happened
but it looks like on the balance of
everything all the data that we have
that possibly maybe probably he died in
a suicide in in
that bunker in berlin berlin when the
soviets were about to
move into that location they are they're
already started capturing parts of
berlin berlin
that's what i can say about this
okay let's see questions by some other
people
is balochistan are the balochis an
indian or an iranian ethnic group they
are an indian ethnic group 100 indian
parts of balochistan are currently in
eastern iran
so if you look at okay let's go to the
map map always maps illustrate
everything properly
let's go to the map
where's the map
here is the map
so where is balochistan
so you see the city the port city of
chabahar over here
here
and you see the port city of gwadar over
so this is all balochistan the makaran
coast all of this is balochistan it is
west of sindh
and
so so approximately half of it i would
say is in present-day pakistan
and the other half of it or at least one
third of it is currently in iran the
balochis are not an iranian
people
they are an indian people no matter what
the historians claim no matter what the
linguists claim the balochi people are
an indian ethnic group they look like
the people of sindh and of gujarat they
don't look
like the people of persia
so even though the persians are
overall
part of the indo-iranian ethnic group
they look somewhat different from
indians today because of the mixing with
the turks and the arabs
some persians are still pure portions
they look more like indians black hair
brown eyes and all that but some
iranians have
a bit of intermixing with it with the
turks and the
arabs but the balochis are properly
indian
so the answer is very simple the
balochis are an indian ethnic group
okay let's take some other questions
vijay vagila says when was is the
gujarat government going to change
the name of ahmedabad
i don't know you need to ask the
government of gujarat
yeah so this this city is named after
the
sultan the great tyrant ahmad
what was his name whatever his name was
it is named after an invader obviously
ahmedabad
so
in the spirit of decolonization we need
to rename the city to the original name
which i think happens to be karnawati so
there has been this demand to rename the
city to its original name for at least
20 30 years minimum
and that's what the i think
i'm not sure if it's the case but i
think there were promises made that this
was this would be done
but yeah it's not been done so i i'm not
the right person to ask this you need to
ask the government of gujarat maybe the
chief minister etc about what is the
status when are we going to do it or
have they actually shelved the plan
to rename the city so maybe there is
some cultural sensitivity maybe it will
cause communal issues i don't know what
it is
so
so you need to ask the government not me
okay
let's see some other questions
they just asks why did isro tie up with
oppo is it in india's interest at all is
oppo chinese company i'm not sure i i
believe it maybe
what is oppo
it's a chinese consumer electronics
company so i think it's very strange
very strange that isro has tied up with
oppo
uh
i don't know why they have done it i'm
not sure if it is in india's interest
for india's space agency to tie up with
oppo maybe it's just a commercial
linkage maybe there is no sharing of
data no sharing of scientific
information maybe there is no
presence of an oppo person
anywhere inside isro maybe that's the
case in which case it's okay
in that case it's okay
but uh i am i'm sure the indian
government is aware of what oppo is of
course they're aware of it and they are
obviously aware of the
national interest uh
the the the fact that isro
is india's space agency it is one of the
most important agencies in india
geopolitically scientifically etc for
india's future
i am sure the right precautions are
being taken
uh
so i think i'm not quite sure why this
has been done i i read up i i heard
about it a couple of days ago i'm not
sure to what extent this tie up is and
what is the purpose of the type maybe i
will look into it study in detail and
maybe i can answer again
in a future episode
how do you explain the difference
between the dravidian and the
indo-european languages the numbers 1-10
are pronounced quite differently
sanskrit latin is closer to sanskrit
tamil are you quite sure my friend that
uh sanskrit latin is closer to sanskrit
tamil
because if you see india's languages
any any language that is classified as
indo-aryan
and any language that is classified as
classified as dravidian you will see so
much commonality at least minimum 40
percent of the words will be in common
more than 40 of the vocabulary of let's
say telugu
at least 40 percent of telugu vocabulary
is sanskrit in origin
similarly for kannada language for the
kannada language 30 40 minimum words are
of sanskrit origin look at tamil at
least 30 words are of sanskrit origin
sangam literature what is sangam the
word sangam is a tamil word for god's
sake
take the names of all the tamil of the
famous tamil people
is that a tamil word it's a sanskrit
name
sanskrit
kamala hassan
shri devi
hema malini
everybody is named after sanskrit words
the entire language is full of sanskrit
words
look at
malayalam
full of sanskrit words there are more
similarities between the so-called
dravidian languages in the so-called
indo-aryan languages then there are
similarities between
any indo-aryan language and a european
language
and yet indo-aryan languages north
indian languages are classified with
europe even though they have way more in
common with the languages of south india
does it make any sense to you
that that north indian languages have
what much much more in common with south
indian languages and yet they are
classified
along with the european languages with
which with with which they have very
little today in common you have to go
deep into the linguistic roots of words
to uncover similarities which points to
a migration outside of india from india
so therefore yeah some numbers here and
there will be pronounced differently and
so on but look at the similarities all
people only focus on the differences
right
people only want to focus on the
differences and they want to kindly to
nicely
tune out
the similarities
people say
hinduism and buddhism are separate
religions
well there is more in common than
different
buddhism is just one of the
philosophical schools of thought of
hinduism of sarathan dharma of the of
the dharmic world
right
the the principles are the same
the values are the same
the teachings are the same
the culture is the same the world view
is the same some minute small
differences philosophical differences
and all that are highlighted to to claim
that there are differences between these
two things and buddhism is a separate
religion apparently
and similarly between the north indian
languages and the languages of southern
india they are they are only focusing on
certain differences and completely
ignoring so much which is in common
so once again there is way more in
common between these two
these two language families or language
groups then there is in common between
indian north indian languages and
european languages
so i totally disagree with this
formulation of two language families
within india the so-called indo-aryan
language family in the so-called
dravidian language family
i think all of these languages have very
very deep roots they evolved together
they evolved in parallel and the roots
go back 70 75 000 years before today
when the first out of africa migration
happened and the first settlement
was done in india
so that is what needs to be uncovered a
priori
our linguists you guys and girls who are
watching me
some of you will go on to become
linguists and historians i want you to
take up this great task
re-examine india's language family is
a priority without making any
assumptions
and without harboring any of the biases
that are
uh taught
in history textbooks by the western
linguists and by the indian colonized
linguists and historians
re-examine these languages from scratch
from zero and you will find the truth
about the origin of india's
wonderful
diverse
linguistic
culture
okay some more questions lots of
questions
i have answered about crispr in the past
um
varun says what is the right way to
study and understand physics
first of all
you need
curiosity
curiosity and
it doesn't apply to physics only it
applies to any field any endeavor that
you can take up is a serious
uh thing to study
first of all you need curiosity you need
to have a thousand questions popping up
in your mind why is why are things like
this why does this phenomenon happen why
does that happen and then you need to be
to study it systematically so you need a
great deal of mathematical knowledge you
have to start from the basics from the
school level college high school level
college level university level in
parallel you have to study the various
texts in physics which teach it uh from
the beginning
so that is the right way to understudy
and understand physics the main thing is
you need to have an open mind you need
to be very curious you need to
be able to ask the right questions and
then study the textbooks systematically
step by step you build a building you
construct a building with the first
floor then second floor third floor
fourth floor you can't go straight to
the top that's what people do people
think that uh there are some people you
know who tell me
i i
i heard a lecture by a scientist for
huffiner a scientist who knows quantum
mechanics so therefore i understand
quantum mechanics quantum mechanics now
i spoke to so-and-so scientists for an
hour he taught me quantum mechanics i
now know what is quantum mechanics this
is the sort of
thing that happens when you don't study
it
properly systematically no one
understands quantum mechanics i have
been studying quantum mechanics for more
than 25 years
i also don't know what quantum mechanics
is telling us there is so much that
needs to be uncovered
right
and i what did i say i did not say i'm
an expert in quantum mechanics i said
i'm a student of quantum mechanics so
always have the right attitude don't
think you're an expert and you and wear
all that thing on your head right
you're always a student you have to be a
student all your entire life
okay more questions
um i have already answered about the
origin of urdu the urdu language
um
let's take some questions which question
shall i take
what's happening in australia why do
they always suffer from disasters
so last year i think there was this
spate of forest fires wildfire that
ravaged the cross across australia
that's the disaster that i can think of
apart from that i'm not sure if there's
any other disaster that's unfolding
there
there was this big spate of forest fires
i think last year it was last year
uh maybe last couple of years so you let
me tell you how forest fires occur
so in the 1990s i think there was this
enormous forest fire in yellowstone
national park
in the united states enormous forest
fire it it burned down a significant
portion of the national park it's a big
forest
so why do forest fires happen
why do they proliferate nowadays
it's because of human intervention you
see fires are a natural phenomenon
fires are caused by lightning strikes
they are caused by
the focusing of sunlight through a water
drop sometimes if the focus happens on a
dry leaf it may ignite may catch fire
there are multiple ways by which fire
can occur
naturally
and what happens when you have a
national park or some forest reserve
that is protected by the government you
have forest rangers and government
officials who are entrusted with the
care of the part of the park what they
do is that the moment a fire occurs they
go and kill it
they keep killing the fire
now naturally if there was no human
intervention the fire would have
occurred it would have burned for some
time it would have taken uh
would have destroyed some part of the
forest and it would have died naturally
that is how nature works
forest fires happen and they eventually
uh die a natural death but when human
intervention happens repeatedly and
forest fires are not allowed
to occur
that's when you are sitting on a ticking
time bomb because a forest fire will
clear some part of the forest at one
time
and make it impossible for a mega fire
to ever happen because when small fires
have happen from time to time to time
it will always create some gaps in the
forests which which will ensure that no
big fire ever happens but when there is
human intervention they keep killing the
forest fire every time and this goes on
for 10 20 years then one day a forest
fire will happen which will be
unstoppable
and no matter how much you try to
intervene it's going to burn and burn
and burn it's going to wipe out a
significant portion of the forest
kill all the animals it's going to be a
disaster beyond your imagination that's
what happened in yellowstone national
park
in the 1990s i think
i visited there
a few few years later
it was you could still i mean more than
a decade later i visited there you could
still see the the effects of the fire
more than a decade after it happened so
it is human intervention that causes
these forest fires i am not sure what
what happened in australia but there was
this serious state speed of forest fires
in australia now when it comes to uh
a place like the amazon rainforest you
have fires happening all the time there
these are artificially set fires
there are these commercial interests
that are trying to wipe out the amazon
forest so that they can cultivate
soybeans and other things there for
animal agriculture because soybeans are
fed to cows and cattle in north america
for their beef industry
so
to make the cows and cattle that big to
get to so much beef beef out of them you
have to feed them soy beans and where do
you grow the soybeans
you cut the
amazon forest you turn that into
farmland and you grow soybeans there so
that's why in brazil they are destroying
the amazon rainforest unfortunate very
very sad
it's going to
it's going to cause problems in the
future
so these are reasons why um you have
such disasters that happen
uh forest fires are caused by human
intervention
these forest ranges they mean well they
say hey there's a fire let me stop it
but hey you should let it burn out on
its own that's how nature works so that
could be possibly one of the reasons why
there was this forest fire in australia
i also heard that somebody had set up a
couple of fires on purpose arson
um
i hear it was an immigrant kind of
person i'm not sure that's what i heard
so yeah there is also a human element to
this somebody sets a fire on purpose and
it causes great deal of devastation
so that's what i can say about this i'm
not sure if if there has been a
significant amount of fires in australia
this year
but yes in the last year or last two
years i certainly saw that on the news
it was all over the news everywhere
pakistan is making a movie on babar with
uzbekistan people
they still believe the turkic invasion
was good you know what mr imran khan the
great
captain sir imran khan said
i don't know what he said he said the
turks ruled us for for centuries and he
said that proudly
imagine
the leader
of a country
saying this proudly that a
foreign
people ruled over my people for
centuries and he was happy about it he
was proud about it
he was talking about india that the
turks were ruled over india for several
centuries that's the claim he made and
he said that proudly today is a
pakistani but the people are the same
right
so he was saying this proudly that these
turks ruled over us for so many years
imagine the
level of mental colonization of mental
enslavement
in the leader of pakistan the prime
minister of pakistan the once once upon
a time the great the great captain of
their sports team cricket team
that is the level of mental colonization
and enslavement that you find in certain
sections of society
in pakistan it's almost prevalent
everywhere in in all people in india i
can see signs of change but still many
of us indians
many of us indians
have this
so the pakistanis yeah even i heard
something like that they they're
they're making a movie or a series
possibly about babur the great babar
with some actors from uzbekistan etc and
they still believe the turkic invasion
it was good yeah it's it's sad it's
unfortunate they are all victims they're
all descended descendants of people who
are
brutalized
but today they are
conditioned
to believe their descendants of turks
which they are not
when i mean you see so many uh
videos on youtube and accounts elsewhere
of pakistan is taking dna tests and you
see what the results are the results i
don't even have to tell you what the
results are they're all indians
right
and so this is the thing you know it's
not propaganda
and they are furthering the propaganda
that enslaves them you have this new
turkic turkish turkish cereal
about jalaluddin jalaluddin of
harassment in which they are portraying
him as some great
great hero and great freedom freedom
fighter the jalaluddin
who lost the battle of the indus took
changes khan the jalaluddin who left his
wife his family his people be behind and
swam across the sindhu river to escape
into india when he knew that his people
would be captured by the mongols the
jalaluddin the big coward
let me tell you what this guy uh
one second
let me show you what a pakistani has to
say about the dean
okay i may not be able to find it right
now but yes so jalaluddin kharagmi was a
big coward but the turks
are now trying to portray him to rewrite
the entire story of this guy and they
are trying to portray him as a great
hero
so that is the power of propaganda
we also have this big film industry but
it unfortunately bollywood right
bollywood and unfortunately it indulges
in anti-india propaganda it maligns
india's civilization and culture and
promotes
and and portrays and and promotes
an image a narrative
of the foreign brutal occupiers of india
as superior to indians as someone who as
people who improved indian society
indian society was downtrodden backward
barbaric primitive and they civilized us
they gave us
culture apparently they gave us the urdu
language
whatever the hell that is
they gave us in the english language how
can you do science without english
so what were indians doing for thousands
of years
so so the thing is we need to
wake up
from our mental enslavement all of us
has some of that
myself included i am sure i have some of
that we need to
consciously identify where our thought
patterns
are problematic
and we need to work on that
so this is a good question
all right
okay some more questions
akshay says do you think nuclear energy
is the future
as it is the most reliable and efficient
form of renewable energy you know
renewable
nuclear energy
is
an excellent
form of energy
and nuclear reactors
they work very well
as long as the design is good as long as
the operation is good they are almost
foolproof
if you program the right fail-safe
mechanisms and all that in there they
will never go wrong they will never
explode they will never leak etc as long
as you follow the right practices it is
an excellent source of energy it takes
very little nuclear fuel to give you a
significant amount of electricity using
the turbine process and all that so i
think it is something that india should
invest in the west and japan are moving
away from it because we know what
happened in fukushima which was a
disaster but it was a completely
avoidable disaster
they did not keep in mind the
possibility of a tsunami and japan is
where the word tsunami came from so it
is something that happens from time to
time in japan
throughout history we know that this
happened right
yesterday i spoke about the attempted
mongol invasions of japan the kamikaze
divine wind that came and swept away the
mongol invasion fleet twice what was
that
so it's strange that uh the fukushima
nuclear plant was did not have
precautions against such an eventuality
but the plant itself was fine
it was a good design but they did not
create a protection against high waves
it was on the seashore right on the sea
coast
and similarly chernobyl was human error
they messed up big time
yeah
and so nuclear accidents have happened a
few times
but i think as long as you take the
right precautions it's a very good
source of energy and like bobby is
saying solar is also good solar energy
is also good
uh it's cleaner yes that is certainly it
is cleaner
so india has a huge potential for solar
energy it is uh the founding member of
the global solar alliance so we clearly
need to focus on renewable clean energy
nuclear energy can form a certain part
of that a certain percentage of that
solar should be a big focus solar energy
is is it's free
right
uh
and india has so much sunlight so we can
certainly become a solar energy super
power
in a few years maybe in a decade maybe
we can uh
derive a significant maybe for more than
50 of our energy from solar maybe 10 20
from nuclear if possible and there are
other uh sources like hydro etc and
there are all kinds of alternatives
available so yes certainly we need to
focus on renewable clean green energy
and nuclear can form a certain
percentage of that
and we need to move away from burning
coal and other fossil
fuels
karna
i've answered that question
okay let us
some people say that aurangzeb built and
funded more temples than he destroyed
how true is it
absolutely untrue
absolutely 100 percent incorrect there
are certain a foreign
there's this lady from from the us
who has been on on a crusade
to uh
to rehabilitate aurangzeb and to
to transform his image from image from
that of a brutal
mass murderer to uh
to a good
philanthropist and social reformer an
enlightened ruler
audrey something her name is
so these are all absolute lies
absolute lies this is completely
incorrect
uh you can look up online all the
records exist of how many temples he
ordered to be destroyed and what other
atrocities this monster perpetrated on
the people of india
okay what else do we have
what else do we have
i'm sure there are lots of comments
coming in i'm unable to see them all
they're coming in very fast
okay let's talk about geopolitics
is it a wise decision for india to shake
hands with china
and keep a distance with america as we
know america is patting our back to back
stab us
will china get along with india answer
me
china can certainly get along with india
so the question is
under what
circumstances
will china get along with india the
answer is
china will get along with india
on an equal footing
when they respect india
today
china
does not respect india china treats
india with contempt
china
shows india as the example of sea this
is what democracy does to a country and
they are right
india is so badly
misgoverned until now until very
recently
even today
the central government is still
struggling
to effect reforms
there are so many internal divisions in
strife in india
there are elections year after year
after year after year after year
there is so much energy and money being
expended
in elections
all the energy of the country is wasted
on this pointless elections year after
year why can't you have one cycle of
elections every five years
but we don't do that we want to keep
this this system going there is so much
corruption
there is so much mismanagement
in so many problems because of the kind
of democratic system we have
adopted
we can adopt a far more efficient
democratic system but this is what we
have adopted
and india's armed forces have
don't have the level of funding they
should have
our economy is not growing at 15 a year
why should it not grow at 15 a year
but there are so many internal problems
so many things are left to the states to
decide
so many matters are federal matters
and even though the central government
wants to take india in a certain
direction certain states don't want to
do that
and they want to go in the opposite
direction there are so many forces
within india that are pulling us in
different directions and these are the
reasons why the chinese don't respect
india
and most importantly india has not
become a nation that has this overt hard
power
teeth
teeth military teeth
and the willingness to use the military
option
so the the day india becomes an economic
power and a military power of that
caliber and it has the political will
to do these things that's when the
chinese will respect us because respect
comes out of fear
in geopolitics respect comes from fear
please understand this my friends
and in other spheres of life also very
often
respect stems for fear from fear
you may not like somebody but you are
forced to respect them
right so when india
gains that level of respect from china
then india and china can get along
famously
but as long as china doesn't respect
india
we cannot shake hands from with china
that's when we need to
uh have other alliances
even though there's maybe temporary
alliances and therefore as of today it
is pointless for india to shake hands
with china chinese will pretend to stay
shake hands but they will continue
their
projects to undermine india and to
crumble india into pieces
so the solution is very simple if you
want respect in on the geopolitical
stage
that respect stems from fear from the
fear of your military actions and your
economic actions you have to rise to
that stature
so that's the answer my friends
okay
any other questions
lots of questions
why is democracy successful in the u.s
is it
let's take a look at the united states
of america um
i have lived there on two different
locations in the us
so i know the country
so what is the u.s like
what is life like in the united states
when you're a kid
when you're a child
what does a child need
a young child needs the support system
of two parents
it needs some things from one parent
which the other parent cannot provide
it needs some other things from the
other parent which this parent cannot
come cannot provide it needs a stable
household the stable love and support
and guidance of two parents
in the us
most the overwhelming majority of
children grow up in broken families
divorced parents they live with either
the father or the mother so there is
this element of uncertainty and whatever
parent they are living with will have a
multi will of multiple
relationships with various men and women
so that is again an element of
instability then the child will go to a
school where they are always bullied
schools the school system in the us is
very abusive
a lot of bullying and other problems as
well
and then when you reach a certain age in
the u.s you do drugs
it is a right of passage every youngster
drug does drugs their parents also know
about it and they expect it to happen
then there is violence shooting and all
that
and now you have
this new culture the woke culture
so
it is a nation that is unfortunately
crumbling
the fabric of society is crumbling
and where is the i mean look
how do you
how do you measure the success of a
democracy
right now the u.s global influence is
decreasing day by day
the chinese are getting more and more
assertive
when was the last time you had a great
us leader great president the last great
president i can think of
is ronald reagan in the 1980s
so i do not see democracy as being very
successful in the us
i do not see that and look at the way
the elections are conducted there
you have a candidate like tulsi gabbard
who is deliberately marginalized she was
not even allowed to be part of the
debates in the democratic party they
keep changing the rules of the uh of the
debates just to exclude her
that is outright rigging
so i disagree with this contention that
democracy is successful
in the united states i think
the indian
form of democracy that was prevalent in
india for thousands of years
is the right form of democracy i don't
care about the us about for india
india needs to revert to its
civilizational
form of democracy
india is the mother motherland of
democracy this is where india is where
democracy took birth
so when india goes back to its own
indigenous civilizational form of
democracy that's when india will take
off
okay so that's my answer my friends
okay
okay srinivas and i spoke about
did ancient indians smoke some say it's
mentioned in atharva veda
and other questions as well i'm not sure
of ancient indians smoked
i know that the use of cannabis
was certainly
prevalent in in certain sections of
society for instance the sadhus
some of the sadhus in certain
denominations of the sadhus
like the agoris etc there is this
um practice of smoking cannabis
ganja they call it right ganja
hemp
so that was certainly part of indian
culture it was nothing that was frowned
upon it is not as far as i know from my
limited knowledge it doesn't seem to be
a habit-forming
uh activity
and tobacco i'm not sure if it was there
and it must have been
present in india maybe some people
smoked so this is an interesting
question
i think uh
in a certain
i've heard that in some texts
uh
smoking is it's at some point in time is
is
perhaps specified as something that can
cure certain ailments
it's it's something i need to revisit
again but it was certainly
prevalent in certain sections of society
it was not something that formed habits
like like tobacco does today because
today tobacco is designed to become a
highly addictive thing i believe that
cigarette tobacco is
more addictive than
than heroin and crack cocaine
it is harder to quit smoking than to
quit the habit of heroin and cocaine so
that's how
dangerous tobacco is today
in the past
indians most likely smoked something
else
it was hemp ganja in some cases and some
other herbs etc
in some other cases so smoking was
certainly there but it was not something
that was prevalent across society
everybody who got up and smoked a
cigarette there was no such thing at all
okay let me take one more questions and
then we can wrap up for today
do we have any
other questions we have lots
um
okay this is by shrieker
do you think that india needs to invest
more on defense forces with additional
forces like marines of the of the us for
more hard power
do you think defense would be
decentralized i think defense should be
completely centralized if you
decentralize defense and leave one part
of the army in each state under each
chief minister it's going to be a recipe
for disaster
an enormous
subcontinent-sized geography like india
needs centralization of power in order
to be run efficiently and governed
efficiently for the long-term interest
of the nation and the people so
the defense forces need to be
centralized and integrated
properly that's the big mission that
general cds general ravath was on and
his successor will take that up and
finish the task that he had taken up now
does india need to invest in
more
forces more manpower and defense no
india needs to invest in
indigenous technology
the 21st century is a century of
technology you may have a 5 million
strong army but if your technology is
obsolete you're going to be wiped out to
the last man by a nation with one tenth
the number of soldiers you have but
superior technology
technology is
a force multiplier
imagine you have a hundred men with
swords
and one guy with a rocket launcher can
wipe them out so technology is one man
with that technology is greater than 100
men with swords
technology is a force multiplier india
needs to invest
in high technology india needs to invest
in
in its navy
in its air force in its missile systems
in cyber warfare
in other forms of warfare which i'm sure
you know about in space technologies
right
so these are the things that india needs
to invest in india can even cut down on
some manpower it will not really harm us
as long as we incorporate better
technologies and and deadlier weapons
in
our arsenal
so that's what we need to do
and that's what i can say
okay my friends we are done for today
thank you so much for the wonderful
questions very interesting session very
lively session and we will keep doing
this next week
so thank you once again it's a privilege
taking your questions and answering and
answering them and interacting with you
all and i will see you
next week in the next session take care
thank you
bye